welcome to untangling the world knot of
consciousness
wrestling with the hard problems of mind
and meaning in the modern scientific age
my name is john vervicky i'm a cognitive
psychologist and
cognitive scientist at the university of
toronto in canada
throughout the entire series i will be
joined in dialogue by my good friend and
colleague
ray enriquez from james madison
university in the united states
throughout we are going to wrestle with
the hard problems of how we can give an
account of a phenomenal like
consciousness
within the scientific world view
how we can wrestle with that problem in
conjunction with the problem that greg
calls the problem of psychology
that is pervasive throughout psychology
which is that psychology has no unified
descriptive metaphysics
by which it talks about mind and or
behavior
throughout this we will be talking about
some of the most important philosophical
cognitive scientific and neuroscientific
accounts of consciousness
so i hope you'll join us through um
welcome again greg it's great to have
you here perhaps
you could introduce yourself again just
so people know who you are
and uh why our work seems to repeatedly
and creatively and constructively keep
keeps converging
absolutely um yes i see so much
relevance in what you do john
[Laughter]
so uh yes i'm a professor of psychology
at james madison university
i'm a clinical psychologist by training
uh but really interested in building
a uh more unified metapsychology uh
that organizes the science of human
psychology in relationship to
psychotherapy
and the overlaps with your integrative
vision for human cognitive science are
quite striking yeah very much i agree
with that
all right and so greg has been sort of
uh i don't know what this is shadowing
kibbutzing looking over my shoulder or
something recent stuff stalking you
[Laughter]
on consciousness
that material is is not going to be made
public
but i am in um in process of turning it
in
uh to uh youtube content uh but
what greg has been uh looking into
uh was some of the recent work i've been
doing
on addressing what's called the hard
problem of consciousness
and i break it up into a bunch of
problems a function problem a nature
problem
um things like that we can get into that
in more detail
and then i also make an argument that
if you address those two questions the
function of the nature
uh question you start to see some very
deep connections between
uh consciousness and uh and fluid
intelligence
uh sort of fluid general intelligence
under the auspices
of ideas around relevance realization
and then i have a sense
that that is connected to
how people are engaged in um extended
mind practices
and so that's sort of uh the
the beehive or ball of wax that uh
we're going to try and at least or
frankenstein man beast
so greg is referring to the fact that in
one of the emails
one of the things he saw in a course
yeah
yeah i referred to uh i refer
to the theory that i worked out with
anderson todd and richard wu
and um
there's one of the marksman james
marshman yeah
uh that that that uh uh
i i called the the huge paper that we
put together to try and end it all
integrate it all together a
frankensteinian man beast of a
of a manuscript um so maybe we can
we can try to play without a little bit
too
so um there's a lot here on the table
and sorry for those of you
watching this is initially a little bit
vague what what what
uh what we're trying to do is you can
see and i welcome it from greg
i mean this is a very serious and
central topic in
human and the understanding of human
ontology
uh but uh greg and i are both playful uh
about it
not because we don't take it seriously
and we're not trying to do our best
about it
but uh everybody has to come to this
topic
with it you know you know a large grain
of humility
uh because this is like um this is the
holy grail
of cognitive science and i think it's a
schopenhauer call it the world not and
it it it's an important place within
uh greg's overarching uh medicine
metacycle technology
so i i i appreciate the
there's the playfulness here um and so
we're going to try and do some serious
play about this topic
um greg how how would you like to start
about yeah so uh
well first off uh you know like you uh
although you're more immediately
entangled in sort of the
phenomenological consciousness
and realizing relevance relationship to
intelligence
but what that is doing for me and that's
what i hope our conversation will unfold
is filling in a wide variety of
different details
around the structure uh sort of this
macro level structure system that i've
been constructing
okay so uh for me what my pitch is
to scholars you talked about sort of
schopenhauer world not
what my pitch is is that modernist
natural
empirical science the language game of
it
the grammar of it had what i call the
enlightenment gap
in it and it didn't give us the right
grammar for talking about mind and
relationship to matter
it also didn't clarify what scientific
knowledge was relative to social
pragmatic knowledge
um and both of those are really
complicated and they're both connected
to why i think the modernist
paradigm of understanding across a whole
host of different issues actually needs
an upgrade
we needed enlightenment 2.0
that enables us to see consilience
from physics to sociology which of
course is what the
large macro model that i built called
the tree of knowledge is all about
right okay and it's like and it's about
i hone in for me on what i call the
problem of psychology
okay which is that it has this identity
of being defined as the science of
behavior and mental processes in all of
the textbook
all right um but the concepts of
behavior and mental processes then
immediately are defined in different
ways depending on which language game or
paradigm
you then adopt now there's no consensus
on what
is meant by behavior and mental
processes
okay and so the science of psychology
actually just translates really into
applying empirical methodology
to whatever the hell it is that people
decide is behavior
mental process uh depending on their
tradition
right right okay
so i believe though that the tree of
knowledge sets the stage to solve
the problem of psychology and what i
mean by that it affords us a descriptive
metaphysical system
to upgrade the modernist language game
so that we can now talk coherently
about behavior and mental processes
so why don't you take us through again
it's really a big
project it's a big project it's a big
project absolutely
maybe zero in on sort of a couple of key
bridge
bridges right yeah so so sometimes it
helps to show some diagrams i'm going to
go ahead and share my screen
and yeah show your diagram real fast
okay so
let me actually i'll first just really
quickly show people
the uh um
this so this is our tree of knowledge
system
okay are you able to see that
nothing so far ah okay maybe oh maybe i
didn't confirm that i needed to share
sorry about that there it is yeah
okay you see it now it's coming up
okay okay now it's up greg okay
uh so here's the tree of knowledge
system okay
and the key insight from the tree of
knowledge system
it's consistent with lots of uh
approaches the most
probably major approach is called big
history so that's
uh this macro view that goes from the
big bang
all the way to the present on the
dimension of
time and complexity which goes from
matter to life to mind
to culture the tree of knowledge got a
couple of really unique features to it
perhaps the most salient and important
for our purposes
is the fact that it sees emergent planes
of existence or dimensions of complexity
and that they emerge as a function of
novel information processing and
communication
feedback systems right okay so you get a
cells communicate and they're storing
and processing genetic information
speaking loosely here
okay then you get animals they're
processing information and communicating
with each other
that is this concept called mind and
i'll be more we'll get into what i mean
by mind
and then ultimately you get humans
processing symbolic information engaged
in person-to-person communication
to create this culture-person plane of
existence
so greg at the bottom of each one of
these there's
uh where it intersects with the open
plane from the one below it
there's a small circle like
justification systems theory
investment theory so i take it that
these theories
perform important epistemological and
ontological bridging functions
that's exactly right they're called
joint points exactly
uh and so at the very base go all the
way back you have quantum mechanics and
general relativity
uh understanding the gravitational force
that is conceptualized as a joint point
between energy and
the pure energy singularity the
emergence of matter okay
and then if you could unify that that'd
be the ultimate theory of
material everything but i'm quick to
point out it's not necessarily a theory
of all things
the evolutionary synthesis is genetics
and natural selection
which i also believe needs to be fused
with modern understanding of cell
behavior
as complex adaptive systems but that
would then give a rise to that
yes and behavioral investment theory is
a framework for
understanding the nervous system uh as
an
investment value system that tracks
salience and relevance in an environment
right right to expend energy and then
justification systems
is about how the human
self-consciousness system emerges
okay right and you and i have talked
about the justification system
exactly when we were together so what i
want to do then
now is just go into all right with that
as a basic background i want to walk you
through where i
am and get to a point where i'm going to
argue that
your what what i think about
consciousness
is a subset of mental processes okay
uh specifically what i will call mind
two
relative to mind one and mind three okay
okay so the background now the first
point you mentioned you could you drew
your attention to behavioral investment
theory
behavioral investment theory gives rise
to a not a neurocognitive
functionalist view of mental behavior
which in many ways should be pretty
common sensical
basically it says what is the nervous
system it's an information
processing cybernetic control system
okay
that's regulating the complex adaptive
behaviors of the animal as a whole
okay okay and what it says is that
there's a layering of of these
information processing mechanisms over
time
and ultimately what you have here then
in the left side of the diagram is a
neurocognitive functionalist
architecture
of the human mind that combines the
evolution
of the nervous system across four layers
one of which is
reactive and the emergence of you know
core instincts that are pretty
constrained
triggered by particular stimuli that are
particular create
illicit reactions and then the learnings
habituation
sensitization you get modal patterns of
activity
in animals but not a huge amount of
flexibility
okay this would have been actually the
state of animals right before the
cambrian explosion according to this
frame
okay which is a that's a when really
then animals
become a much more diversified about 550
million years ago
yeah i've heard that they are one of the
one of the current theories is the
driver of that
complexification was the evolution of
eyesight
yes yes okay and and actually what i
believe is actually happening
there's a eyesight site actually then
gets hooked into motor control
and you get an integrated sensory motor
control system
and another then driver goes from the
associative reflexive reactive kind of
systems into a much more operant
online consequential learning system
right right right so get speaking gets
becomes much more predictive
in its functionality exactly and and
much more regulatory and this gives rise
to what i call the second layer here
which is the operant
experiential layer okay uh
whereby you have perceptual holes
tracking approach states relative to
avoidance states
and then emotion you get the emergence
of emotion as an
emoting energizing system
okay that's basically trying to regulate
the discrepancy of the appraisal
relative to where you want to be
motivationally right okay
okay so that's an operant experiential
and that's exploding
uh in terms of the cambrian explo you
know period and you see
com animals with complex active bodies
then you get the emergence of
increasingly more sophisticated cortical
systems that allow for imaginative
thought to make predictions via
simulation
of possibilities so they're not nearly
as anchored to
the stimulus regulatory consequential
system
but in fact can project themselves over
time
based on you know predictive models okay
i th there's an online bayesian system
and now there becomes a bayesian system
that's predicting possible outcomes and
starting to simulate consequences
down various behavioral investment
pathways right
okay and and that's that brings us
through
the bird and mammalian cortical lines
uh at various levels of sophistication
with a lot of species specific
architecture
but this is the basic gestalt okay
okay and then you get with humans you
get a
an interpreter symbolic information
processor
that emerges into the language
acquisition device
okay so this gives rise to a
four-layered view of reactivity
operand experiential imaginative
thinking and
linguistic narration right all right
and this is also organized in
relationship to what we know about
memory in terms of this right here is
your sort of sensory memory function
okay you have a working memory system of
about you know
10 to 20 30 seconds uh and the badly
phenomenological
and sketch pad loops right
okay i know we're using a lot of
technical language here we can stop it
and then you have a long-term memory
storage systems a procedural
point of view episodic memory and
semantic memory
right that organizes okay and this is
then
your neurocognitive functionalist view
but it's basically anchored to thinking
about the mind and really
like neurocognitive functions i mean you
can just basically say there's input
there's functional relationship between
output we can assess these from a third
person perspective
okay okay and it's being mediated
presumably all
you know by brain function we can we can
talk about brain
uh that relation here we have the model
then
so that's a neurocognitive model this is
a model of
conscious experience now we're getting
into then the first person
phenomenological model we've talked
about this model before we have a first
person experiential
a private narrator and a public self
with three dimension
three kinds of filtration between these
yeah
okay so that's that's a background now i
want to get into the real
clear descriptive metaphysical mind and
i'll then come back
ultimately and delineate mine too which
is going to be
this space right in here the
experiential in narrator but gives rise
to that perspectival point of view
okay okay yeah very nice
very nicely okay so now we come back to
my concern
ultimately and we have what i believe is
this big problem with psychology one of
the core problems that really defines
psychology is its history and subject
matter
is what is the relationship between
consciousness and behavior
okay a lot of reasons for why this is
complicated but one of them is an
epistemological reason
which is consciousness is available
through the first person interior
perspective what ken wilbur calls the
interior perspective
okay and behavior is available through
the exterior or
general third person view and amenable
to observation measurement
and the epistemology of modern natural
science
okay so that's one of the big problems
and this is why i'm so excited as i
think you and i together
can hone in on the functionalist and
metaphysical descriptions
of consciousness in relationship to a
big picture behavior and put stuff
together in a way that really
tightens the relations between the
concepts and gives rise to a picture of
the whole
that's that's that's a very awesome
proposal okay
keep going please okay and what we're
trying to do and delineating you were
very you know when you talked earlier
like hey are
all these different things there's an
issue of uh this really is a body
physical and living behavioral brain
cognitive computational consciousness
phenomenological
and self and self-consciousness problem
that's why just to give you an idea how
thorny this thing is right it's got all
these different elements
okay well said well so so then what
we're trying to do is now try to figure
out the interrelations between all these
parts and what my system
orients me to is actually uh dividing up
mental processes into three different
domains
based on their ontological reference and
our epistemological consideration
okay so we have these two
epistemological considerations
behavioral investment theory gives rise
to conception
mind one which basically is an exterior
view
of animals engaging in functional
awareness and response
okay so if i see my dog barking at a cat
we can say he's exhibiting from a third
person perspective that's a functional
awareness
i don't know how his consciousness i
don't know what it's like to be him
but i can see obviously there's a
stimulus he's responding to it in a
functional way
right okay and so we can then define
those overt mental behaviors in the
traditional behavioral ethology
or behavioral science way and because
i'm pro
proposing like you and others at a broad
level that nervous system is a
information processing system so there
are neurocognitive processes that are
mediating
and regulating coordinating we can use
whatever term those
behavior of the animal as a whole okay
okay we then get into the sticky issue
of mind two which is this first person
witnessing function
but which we you and i obviously based
on what we can dialogue with each other
know to be then our first person
experience of subject to being
this is going to connect to
consciousness and that the interior
epistemology
and then finally as humans we have
self-conscious justification
okay which has private i can talk to
myself privately
or i can engage in public justification
that's right
okay so now if we look at it here we
have an external
view this is sort of in pinkish because
we have to we can see the brain we can
see it's in
activity and then we infer functionally
the information relations
yeah okay we have mind two being
basically all first person
and then we have this interesting
relationship between mine three as both
being private
but also public
so um the just
to ask a couple of mapping questions
it sounds like we could talk very
effectively
because we do in artificial intelligence
uh
right at level mind one uh we talk about
intelligence there
and then mind two seems to be what
uh and you have it labeled that way uh
you sort of the domain of
consciousness and then and i like the
way that you're keeping these distinct
and then mind three
sort of the locus of this is
self-consciousness
but the self-consciousness has both uh
how i'm
conscious to myself and then how i'm
conscious of myself and presentation to
others is that is that a failure very
excellent
excellent okay and because i pay a lot
of attention like marsha mcluhan
to the medium of the information
processing system
the nature of language unlike the nature
of phenomenology
the nature of language is that it's
transparent to the skin i just talk
i can't i can't you can't experience
what redness
is like to me but i can share what i can
tell you what redness is like to me
in the exact same medium and there and i
mean you and there's
there's the you know going back to
wittgenstein the very powerful set of
arguments around the idea
that there's no such thing as a private
language that language is
that language is constituted by being
inherently shared with others
it's an inner subjective phenome so here
you have a text that identifies these
actually three different
domains of mine one as having different
epistemological and ontological
considerations
so mind one is generally exterior okay
mind two interior and mind three
actually is intersubjective and
constituted in the inner subjective
culture person plane of existence
right right okay you know and by the way
you're often talking about the
relationship between personhood
self-consciousness culture socialization
in your dialogue and i totally agree
with that that's that
that's the emergence into a
culture-person plane of existence
right so yeah so yeah i would put
the ontology of personhood uh where you
had sort of
mind three this also this also brings up
the fact
that what's suggested by this the
diagram the one on the right
um is that there's a lot of confused
talk about consciousness because it's
relationship
to the domain of intelligence below it
and
the the domain of self-conscious
personhood above it
is they're often not adequately
distinguished from each other
they're often conflated together in a
confused and confusing fashion
which gives rise to huge amounts of
equivocation and accidental
gets tied into the conversation
yeah very much very much right okay so
here's the last uh thing for right now
also then show you okay so now
here's just a clear representation of
the map so we can now have a vocabulary
to hone in
on and then i'll hand it over to you and
hear you riff off of
sim and uh i'm super excited about your
adverbial and adjectival qualia and i
got all sorts of interesting things so
but just so now so i want to hand this
lexicon back to you so we have a overt
behavior watching somebody do something
from an exterior perspective watching my
dog bark
mind 1b okay
and then we have mind 1a which refers to
the information
instantiated in the nervous system
that's creating a hierarchical
regulation system
perhaps a simulated you know scale
invariant
multi-layered modeling system okay
but into then that somehow gives rise to
and this is now we can talk about the
ontology of this
that first person witnessing that we can
identify as mine two
there is the narrator of mine three uh
you talk about how
rene de tocque talked about how the
subjective mind touches itself
yeah and for me this is where the
self-conscious
access to the phenomenology happens in
the strange
loops of narrative and experience yeah
okay and then this is what we would
share like
as if we take a transcript of this um
this exchange into mine 3b right um
and the ch so so i and the tree of not
the the updated tripartite model by the
way
um provides lots of articulations about
the dynamic relations between these
domains
okay and your model provides
the architecture for understanding and
this is what i didn't have at all
but but the hierarchical layering okay
across the domains
uh to give rise to the interface between
the emergence of
the witnessing function the emergence of
perspective on participatory knowing
and and all of that intricacy so that's
what i want to then
hand back over to you and say i see you
building a model basically of mine 1a
and the mind two
consistent with mine three you know and
articulating the
functional and metaphysical elements
that really fill in that's exactly right
that's the project
um that i'm interested in um yeah that's
oh wow uh nice slides okay
i don't have anything like that to put
into the discussion but
uh wow so that's very helpful and uh
i will try as much as i can to use um
your helpful vocabulary um and
where i refer to my own
we can negotiate the mapping although
you've already indicated some of it
um so
the place where that um
gets well we've already said there's a
place where a lot of confusion comes in
there's a lot of equivocation
to give one clear example for people
watching
uh people will equivocate between a
a mind what you call mind one a third
person perspective sense of information
that is completely measurable
right it's just a right a probabilistic
relationship between events
that rules out alternatives reduces
uncertainty completely cybernetic
account
uh what i often call technical
information or key information
and then information in the sense of uh
semantics uh right having
you know more colloquially having an
idea so
uh there if you take a look at that uh
for example a newspaper
there's all there's most people would if
i asked what's the information in the
idea they
they would think of the semantic
information the set of ideas they could
call
but the technical amount of information
is
much more comprehensive and that is how
each little
uh mark of black on the paper has a
probabilistic mark
uh relationship to the kind of mark that
is going to come next
to it and right etc etc and then that
amount of information
and so what people often do without
realizing it is they talk about well
there's
information flowing in the nervous
system and then it flows into working
memory
and that you know and what's the problem
it's just all information flow
and what they're doing is equivocating
between two different meanings
of information in fact there's a lot of
work being done i think you said i sent
you the one article
on where people are trying to do the
very hard
mathematical and theoretical work
philosophically
challenging work of bridging between
those two senses of information yeah
yeah yeah actually i'll throw a third
out there that i think is important to
differentiate
okay so so and the theoretic one has its
roots largely in just for people if
you're going to track it look up claude
shannon
um and his he's a newton of of theoretic
information basically he's unbelievably
influential
um and then the semantic one's a lot
fuzzier
i mean semiotics and other kinds of
notions but
it's a that's a fuzzy one but it's the
other thing if you there's a little book
called a little book on
information and what it means i don't i
don't remember the author sorry forgive
me
um but it starts off with the basic the
information processing schematic
which i think is another thing that
people mean which is basically you have
a translator
okay an input function translator and
then you have a recursive processing
loop which usually has some sort
of memory storage function okay that can
create some
you know computational processes and
then an output function
okay that then regulates so you have
this is what i call the information
processing schematic
okay in r which then adds to another
intuition notion about information
relative to the semantic and theoretic
so what what's that notion do you think
well i just think that that's what
people sort of oh oh here's
like when you talk about oh i'm
processing information or that person
but
they'll have a notion of that schematic
okay not necessarily to to and to
differentiate
and in fact the article that you sent me
um see
they actually go all the way down into
physical there they actually try to
create
a gestalt of a semantic theoretic
conception all the way down to
atoms to scale okay but at the end of it
you'll notice because i have this
categorical
system there yeah but that matter they
don't have an information processing
system
they actually say that so it's like yeah
you need all three actually what i think
you know when we jump up to life it is
an information processing complex
adaptive system
that's predict utilizing informational
forms to predict
particular outcomes across scale and
then somehow has a semantic
say no i get that so there's that's good
so
um so in addition to the technical sense
of information the information theoretic
sense
the shannon sense um and then in
addition to
the semantic sense that's being really
argued about a lot now between
representational
and inactive account cognition you're
proposing
and other people are i think uh
dreyfus is doing this and i think the
work i'm doing you're proposing this
intermediate
uh we might call it a functionalist
account
technical information is being used
within intelligence
which is so we could put it here
i'll try um we've got sort of uh you
know in
just in the physical environment there's
uh technical information
and then as you said there's some
functionless configuration
uh that's uh that turns it into
information processing that is in some
sense
you know intelligent there's some
functional ability there
and then uh and then beyond that
there is the sense of information not
uh as just intelligent uh
behavior uh information processing not
just intelligent behavior
but there's a a further sense which is
this this sense as i and you
are right to say that it's very nebulous
but this that's the sense that bears
intentionality
you know that i have thoughts about
things yep
i can refer to things etc and that kind
of information
so that's and sorry if we're burdening
uh the audience but what we're trying to
point out is
and and and we're negotiating between us
here
is the ways in which when you eat when
you start to talk about this stuff
you have to slow down and take
very great care because the potential
for equivocation
uh between um all these
levels ontological levels and between
the various epistemological
methodologies
is like the chances that you're going to
run an equivocation are almost
overwhelming
if you don't slow down and make
distinctions go
carefully this is why i and i think greg
will
share this with me i am very critical of
a lot of popular discussions
about consciousness and how it can't be
reduced to physicalism
and things like this and i'm not trying
to voice my view on greg or anything
but i think he would share with me a lot
of this that goes on in the public
uh domain it is it's i
i understand that it's often done with
good intention and in good faith but the
conclusions that people draw
are seriously undermined by the fact
that they're almost
always being caught up in major
equivocations
uh without realizing it that undermine
the plausibility of the claims that are
being made so
would you agree with that greg i i
applaud it
i mean you know my my hook in and trying
to get people's attention is
is that's that is so true on the whole
concept of psychology
you know yeah that's why and and
cognitive science deals with this that's
why you're you know you open it up you
know cognitive and behavior
conscious and consciousness is like the
sort of the holy grail of this
equivocation
yeah yeah very much so uh 100 agree
right so that's why this is a hard thing
to do and
i'm just going to forewarn you know greg
and i are going to have several
conversations on this this is not going
to be something
that's going to come to closure in you
know the hour and 15 minutes we have
together now
uh we have planned to have sort of a
series of conversations
where we go through this complexity uh
with the care
that we at least we hope that i've just
said is needed
for this topic um i i would be so bold
as to say
that if you watch a video that claims to
give you grand conclusions about
consciousness and or personhood
um and it's like only 30 minutes longer
or less
then chances are it's wrong um
and again not to be arrogant or elitist
it's not about our expertise it's about
the difficulty of the problem that is
being addressed
and it has to be very seriously
appreciated
by people because
on one hand it is one of the most
important questions and it has
ethical and existential and religious
and spiritual input
that's one of the reasons why greg and i
are so interested in it
and i get we all should be thinking
about it
but the fact that we all should be
thinking about it doesn't mean that we
can just
sort of think about it without taking
great care to first of all
really formulate the problem really
really well
um as some of you know in other
arguments i make in my work
problem formulation is more than half of
problem solving
and if you just if your problem
formulation is largely transparent to
you
and you just leap into the problem and
um
you're gonna you're gonna it's a
nightmare it's a nightmare
so what i'd like to do is to start and
you know great
great i probably have about a half an
hour um and like i said
we're gonna keep doing this but um
i'd like to start with uh first of all
you know getting clearer about the
problem
and so one of the ways there's
two aspects to this so greg i'm gonna
talk for a bit um
yes no this is what go okay
there's two aspects to this uh getting
clear about the problem
there's one and and this is a method
that's familiar to those of you who
see an awakening for the meeting crisis
there's a historical aspect
that needs to be understand very
understood very seriously
uh and the i'll just do a gist of that
here and there's also a structural
aspect of the problem the gist of the
historical problem is to understand
um why we got why the cartesian solution
became sort of the fundamental grammar
uh for how
we talk about all of this stuff and why
it's not
and here's the point that people don't
get that that grammar
is deeply deeply interwoven with the
scientific worldview
so trying to solve the problem
right it gets you immediately enmeshed
with
the fundamental way in which the
scientific world view is constituted
this is why it's a hard problem so
you've got to you've got to be really
really careful
about your attempt to solve the problem
without talking about
its bearing on your understanding of the
scientific world view
so that's the historical thing right so
can i just add something real actually
please please in other words you've been
socialized
with a grammar that probably isn't up to
the task
yes yes very much very much that's a
yeah
that's a good way of putting it i hadn't
thought of the sociocultural aspect
that's a good way of putting it
the structural part of the problem is
that there's actually
two problems um and
we've tended unlike descartes who kept
the two problems together
we've tended to separate these two
problems often
uh apart uh so what are those two
problems
one is the function problem is what is
what does consciousness do uh and this
is
this turns out to be actually a very uh
very difficult problem because it
doesn't it
here's to make it problematic for you it
doesn't look like you need consciousness
you can do so many complex
intelligent sophisticated things like
you are understanding my language right
now
trying to get computers to that is very
hard that's a really
complex task all of that is happening
below your consciousness
all that happens is you get these sounds
and then you get in consciousness
ideas but how those sounds get converted
into like that all of that processing
massively complex
very intelligent is going on
unconsciously
so why is it that we have consciousness
when we can do so much deeply
sophisticated
deeply intelligent behavior without
consciousness so that's the function
problem
i'm not i'm not giving any kind of
answer i'm just laying out the problem
no it's crucial to be clear about it
right and then there is what i call the
nature or the generation problem
this is the problem which greg has
already pointed to with his mouth
so elegantly this is the problem of
how does something like consciousness
emerge within an otherwise physical
world
now putting it that way is simplistic
and i'm doing it that way to
problematize it
because there is the intervening
important variable
of life in both greg and i think there's
something like a deep continuity
hypothesis between mind and life
and life and self-organizing matter
we'll come back to that
but just to put it out as a problem it's
like how does
consciousness which seems to not not
have any of the central properties of
matter
how does it emerge from like the
material realm
now one sort of common answer to that as
well
it doesn't there's two separate
substances
the problem with that is that is not
a solution uh to the nature problem
precisely because you get you get what
is called the mind brain or the mind
body problem
which is if they are two substances
that share no properties in common right
so matter
is takes up space right it has
physical energy it has electromagnetism
to it
uh it has resistance and inertia blah
blah blah blah
and consciousness doesn't seem to have
any of those properties
and consciousness seems to have
intentionality and subjectivity
and a qualitative feel to it and matter
has none of those meaningful attributes
how do they causally interact there's
nothing
in terms of which matt
matter has to sort of contact or radiate
or generate a field how does it interact
with mind that has no material
properties
and how does mind that has no material
how does my mind lead to the moving of
my body and don't say
well the information in your mind gets
the information in your nervous system
because that's just the equivocation
that's just the equivocation
so most people think that descartes
solution
which was to say well there's a
separation of mind and body
while it has actually a very plausible
solution in his historical context
it's ultimately not a viable solution
precisely because
the mind-body problem turns out to be a
just a devastating problem and you can't
leave it
unresolved it's metaphysically
unworkable
i'm unworkable and it's also ethically
and existentially unworkable well
there's
yeah because i mean if if if i don't
have an answer about how
mind and body interact i can't get any
evidence about your mind from your body
right that's interesting yeah i can't
pick up on other minds uh
and that of course has huge and i mean
that had ethical consequences
descartes felt no compunction and
descartes was not an evil twisted man
but descartes had no compunction with
doing you know
a vivid section on live animals dogs
right because
he said you know that's just movement of
a body like a bell ringing
right because there's no evid i can't
get from
their bodies to any evidence that they
have anything like consciousness
right so there's all kinds of
consequences there
absolutely so here's the the thing
uh that we have to do we have these
sort of we might think of it as a
triangle of problems that need to be
addressed um one is we need
an account of what this consciousness do
and then an account of what
consciousness is not in the sense of
it's
a phenomenological description that's
not irrelevant but
what consciousness is in the sense of
how does it fit into this world view
right the nature or generation problem
and
we have to remember that we can't answer
that question
from some a historical god-like
perspective
because we are a mesh in a cultural
cognitive grammar
that has us thinking about this and
biasing us and talking about this
in certain ways that you could make a
good case are plausibly preventing us
from framing the question the problem in
the right way
i think that all and i've argued and
greg has seen these arguments
that the what makes this
very challenging for us but is a
responsibility that you can't avoid is
that all three of these problems
have to be approached in an integrated
manner
that if you try and address the function
problem without addressing the structure
problem
or the history problem or any one of
those like if you try
up answer one of these in isolation the
other two undermine you
in a very very significant and powerful
way what i've been trying to do in my
work
is come up with an approach that will
allow us to begin to frame
how to answer those three in the
integrated
but also very challenging manner that is
needed
so that was a long setup but uh
turn it back to you greg well i mean
it's just a very important
part of the context you know i did a 10
problems as you know because we did the
11th problem
the first thing i said was the problem
of language games
is a nightmare here yeah yeah yeah yeah
and so that's a short way of saying
why that preamble and contextual element
is absolutely essential
to enter into the arena of this
conversation yeah
i think so so one of the things i
i i might want to uh propose
we we do is we might want to
like have uh like maybe
we meet next time we could go a little
we could zero in on
maybe the historical context and why the
cartesian framework
beat out the aristotelian and the
neoplatonic and what does that mean for
how we
are how we tend to think about this and
then
maybe take a look at um
some of the uh most
powerful versions out there right now
that attempt to address the heart
problem
and how they're often a structural
solution or a functional solution
and so we could sort of we could
dedicate time to each one of these and
then
in detail how does that sound to you as
a proposal
hey that sounds certainly certainly good
to me it sets up the whole
you know the the context and the framing
so you have to
you know uh to enable that so absolutely
so
just a foreshadow because i don't we i'm
not going to get it
into too much today because i don't want
to overburden this by making it too long
um and
one of the things that i'm going to try
and argue
is that if we get
uh if we try and use the method
of cognitive science which is the design
stance
which has deep analogs to that
historical schema
that greg presented to you like if we
and we move sort of evolutionary history
but
not in a hit like not just sort of in a
historical representation but
if we tried to design a a system to make
it intelligent
what would we do and what would be the
steps of design
um and what i'm going to argue
is that as we design intelligence we
start to find
important features uh
about consciousness at least the
functionality of consciousness
that start to emerge and we start to see
that that
well that's what i'm gonna argue at
least you start to see that the
intuition that we all carry
that we attribute consciousness normally
where we attribute intelligence and vice
versa
probably has a theoretical relevance
there is in fact probably a deep
connection between
uh fluid intelligence and the
functionality of consciousness
and then the next argument will build on
that is
so as i build intelligence i get the
functionality of consciousness and then
as i build the functionality
of consciousness i start to get some of
the phenomenology
of consciousness right um and that's
and and that's uh that has to do with
stuff that greg uh
both uh likes the adverbial qualia
versus adjectivo qualia
and the participatory and perspective of
learning but stuff i think he also wants
to challenge me on
which is ultimately but yes but it's
still the hard problem and
i get that and that's well we're
breaking the problem up
john okay so it's like it's crumbling in
some ways there are a couple of key
points you know the
the adjecti i think we both agree the
actual emergence of experience and what
is it
constituted by the neuroelectro binding
problem
field you know whatever that we have a
lot of there's hand waving
that emerges there is there is and so
yeah
and full disclosure neither one of us
claimed i in i'm not claiming any sort
of exhaustive
competition right but the the
the question is whether or not
we can make such progress
on not only formulating the problem but
starting to generate some insightful
response to that problem formulation
so that we get us a plausible sense that
this goes from being something that is
ripping our ontology apart to a
difficult
problem that will be situated within a
new
revised ontology exactly yeah and
that's what okay so this is what's so
exciting for me okay so when i'm
learning your system you know yes you
left
what i what i always thought of is the
heart problem you left it
but you circled it and it shrunk yeah
yeah yeah
and that and that caused light bulbs in
my head and that's why i stalk you
okay so right okay so so and the light
bulb you can you say a little bit give
me at least a little t at least for me
this is super exciting
you differentiate adjectival qualia okay
from this uh uh adverbial qualia
here-ness and now-ness uh you know and
and
and there's evidence for it from the
eastern tradition and
and how that all works can you do you
want to give a teaser on that or do you
want to build up to that
well i do want to build up to it i do
because i do think
that's uh i mean that the distinction
between
that and then the distinction between
the qualia and subjectivity
understood in terms of you know the
participatory knowing of and through
respect travel knowing
those are sort of the big conclusions uh
that i that i want to build towards and
i want to show how they come
out of uh you know
attempt via relevance realization theory
uh to build an account of general fluid
intelligence and how
we get a lot of the phenomenology along
and greg is right i
i don't claim to have fully solved uh
the hard problem because i don't have an
account of adjective what i call
objective qualia like the blueness of
blue
and we'll get we'll get to that as we
get into these discussions
uh but and thank you for saying that
greg because
that means a lot to me uh you know the
the the heart problem has sent has at
least been shrunk
um and because the issue of
at least one meaning of subjectivity and
important aspect
of the phenomenology of consciousness
which as greg said is this
adverbial sense of the hereness and
nowness and togetherness
of our conscious experience i think um
that's where
the nature of consciousness and the
function of consciousness can be given
an integrated account so um
this is a long journey that we're going
to be greg and i are
going to be taking together we're going
to be going back and forth
and as you can see you know we're sort
of zooming in and out
uh we're zooming in on the phenomena and
then via greg's
excellent work we zoom out to yes but
what does this mean
right in terms of the overall
metaphysical position
place of psychology etc and then we
zoom back in and you know greg has also
done a lot of work with all of the
problems
so all right um there's a lot here
and it is very promissory i know uh but
what uh what we're promising you uh
is uh we're gonna we're doing this in
really good faith and
um we we both think um i believe that a
kind of
a of a dialogical format is the better
way of trying to present this
information
than just a straight monologue um so i'm
gonna
in the in the spirit of dialogue i'm
gonna turn it back over to greg and uh
but
what he would like to say right now well
i mean you know this is
yeah exactly this is a this is a journey
i i wanna
echo a couple of points um and that is
what exactly are we talking about is
super crucial
you know right and what what are our
shared reference points
and to be very clear uh to ensure that
we're not equivocating
and overlooking that because that
happens all the time so that's one key
point
the second key point that you're um you
made
around equivocation and sort of the
grammar of our reality is that
we inherit through the modernist
language systems
the society kind of bakes in a dualism
a cartesian dualism okay science
has a physicalism and you and i will
talk some about physicalism versus
naturalism
okay i look forward to that and and
and why i hesitate to use physicalism
sometimes as a word but
but at an ontology level you and i are
exactly the same place so that's a
that's a
but it shows language game issues that
are problematic
okay um and i'll come back to my point
about
what i really believe this is an
enlightenment gap dynamic i believe that
the
collapse of psychology so you know my
point is physics
energy matter their interactions yes
quantum mechanics general relativity
blew up some really interesting
questions but that system at a basic
consensual definitional level
remains okay you go into chemistry and
although there's debate about exactly
what life is you know is the coronavirus
alive as it sits there on the table
generally not but sort of right but
nonetheless everyone can
circle uh bacteria is alive a tree's
alive we know what life is relative
okay but what is mind what is behavior
there's no consensus okay
so that's crucial to the enlightenment
gap
i i agree and so i mean the the there's
sort of a semi-technical name for this
problem
in the literature um it's called the
mark of the mental
or the criterion of the cognitive uh
alliteration that often and we struggle
you know mental causation
and the philosophical issues but here's
what i want to make because actually
this links us back to this whole series
on dialogos okay and dialectics all
right
and the kairos of our moment so i'll
sort of just sort of echo and
so that while we're on this journey is
very academic journey
all right uh you know i'm a
psychotherapist here in the midst of the
meeting crisis we're seeing the
connections between our knowledge
systems philosophy and where the world
is
correct totally i believe that the
meaning making crisis
what does it mean to be human the way in
which modern science
could not navigate this language game
okay and how what does it mean if i love
my spouse
okay and who am i and what does my life
matter
about how we talk about those things is
is central to how we live okay and we
have a
impoverished grammar in relationship to
that and i believe
crucially that the 21st century's crisis
that we see pertains to that
impoverished grammar
okay so if we can navigate the grammar
and maybe not solve the hard problem but
if we
hone it in and then actually have a
definitional language and scientific
empirical systems
that fill that in put it on top of
biology
okay the potential that that plays a
crucial role
in addressing the meaning crisis or at
large and
ushering in a sort of enlightenment 2.0
vision i think is very
very real i mean i think it's very
plausible
i i agree and i think that was very
eloquently
and elegantly stated um so um yeah
i agree i i mean greg and i are
academics and we would be working on
this
regardless probably in one sense but uh
both of us are much more concerned
with the relevance that this has uh to
well the meaning crisis and and and it's
great said the fact that
we just don't we can't situate ourselves
um as he said well how do i situate the
fact that i love
my partner into the world view
that is supposed to be the ultimate
authoritative worldview
of this culture and the answer right now
is you can't you just can't
and we both think that that doesn't just
sit out there
like some intellectual problem it's
like you know it it it
permeates you and your cognition and
your attitudes and your
self-interpretation
and your self-model in powerful ways
that affect your relationships to
yourself to each other the world
and often cause distress suffering
and conflict in a way that could be
significantly ameliorated
and so that's why uh we also uh
well i know because i've talked to greg
and he shares this with me that there's
an important
existential ethical and ultimately and
we'll get to this at some point
spiritual spiritual
um implication of all of this
that needs to be taken very seriously
and i would also make the reverse
argument that if you do have serious
serious
spiritual ethical existential
concerns that if you really want to
wrestle with them
you are going to bump up into this
problem that greg and i are centering on
and you don't have to solve it but
you do have to acknowledge it and it
bears some responsibility to it if
because if you leave this unchanged
it will swallow up your attempts
to deal with the spiritual ethical and
existential issues to a very significant
degree
so there's two ways in which this what
we're doing here
should be in some sense relevant to
everybody i mean that sounds grandiose
uh but i think
it's actually the case completely agree
friend i mean this is
it's it's at the center uh or it's one
of the center points
in a nexus of understanding uh whose
absence
is i believe deeply relevant to the 21st
century meaning crisis
and and and if the puzzle pieces can be
juxtaposed
um especially then bridge two practices
of dialectic into dialogues
and all of that uh that's that's the
restructuring to build common ground
in a new ethos um yeah i agree
i agree so that's exactly right uh
uh greg is involved in uh christopher
massive prieto and i are putting
together an anthology
inner and outer dialogues about uh this
whole
idea about dialectic ideologues
and what greg is putting his finger on
here is exactly right that
taking sort of this what you might call
philosophical scientific
endeavor around this world not problem
of mind and consciousness and then
transforming
in partnership because it can only be
done in partnership with others
transforming our cognitive cultural
language and
thought so that we can
garner and appropriate uh whatever
insights we have from tackling this
difficult problem
back into how we live our lives and how
we make
meaning together yet that's that that is
a crucial thing
we need to be doing it and again uh greg
is also involved in that project he's
contributing to that anthology
um as well um so i think greg this is a
good place to
end our our session today because i
think we've got good formulation
uh greg and i'm probably gonna meet
every couple of weeks
and go through like this step by step by
step
and then unpack it for people
um and so i think we'll also make a bit
more effort
on both of our parts to answer
uh respectful questions
that come up in the comment section um
i'm
not obligating myself or greg to respond
to trolls
or people who simply want to tell us
that they have the answer
um but people who want to participate
uh with humor and humility
and insight and good good faith
questioning
we'll make an effort to be more
interactive also well i'm going to make
an effort i think greg would too
absolutely absolutely again this is a
the shared conversation
uh when done in good faith uh and
clarity about the nature of the arena
we're in i will only enrich
the process great okay so greg
uh we'll be meeting again in a couple of
weeks and
what i'm proposing we do there is we we
zero in
and we isolate it at least initially we
can't keep it isolated for the argument
i gave
but we zero in on sort of the historical
framework and really
yeah why are we in this mess around
consciousness
and then and then and then we'll just
keep going through it step by step how's
that
perfect perfect thanks so much friend
yeah that's great thank you so much
thank you for those excellent diagrams
you guys should know going forward uh uh
greg will always often have nice
diagrams and i won't because
he's much better at this than i am but
uh
thank you very much and we'll talk soon
okay
fantastic thank you